Hello everyone, welcome back to English
Pod, my name is Marco, and I'm Erica.
And today we are going back in time.
That's right, we're visiting the 1950s.
All right, so we are
going to the year 1950,
and well, we are going
to look at some of
the typical and common words and
phrases that were used back in that year.
Yes, all of these words and
phrases you might still hear today.
But they are really a
little bit old-fashioned.
All right, so we have
some words that we need
to look at before we
listen to our dialogue,
so let's look at these
words in vocabulary preview.
vocabulary preview.
We have two words we're
going to hear in the dialogue.
The first one, sock hop.
sock hop.
A sock hop.
Okay, now this is very old-fashioned
and probably not used anymore.
No, not used anymore, but
a sock hop is a school dance.
Okay, so all the kids after school would
get together and dance rock and roll.
Exactly.
And well, it's very popular and very common
among American culture in those days.
Yes, in 1950.
So you would still maybe see
this in a movie or something, yeah.
And our second word is still
used today, Sadie Hawkins Dance.
Sadie Hawkins Dance.
All right, a Sadie Hawkins Dance.
So a Sadie Hawkins Dance is a dance when
the girls ask the guys to be their date.
Okay, so it's a party and
the guys don't invite the girls.
No, the girls invite the guys.
Okay, so it's a little bit
of a reverse of roles there.
Yes.
That's interesting.
So in this case, the
girls have to come up
to the guys and say, "Hey, do you
want to go to the dance with me?
" Very good.
So this still happens
today in North America,
so you will probably
hear it some time.
And I guess now
we could listen to our
dialogue for the first time and
it takes place at a high school.
Hey, it's Tracy.
How are you doing?
I'm swell, Sandy.
Hey, listen, you want to go to
the sock hop with me this Friday?
It'll be a blast.
First of all, it's the Sadie Hawkins Dance.
The girls got to ask the guys also.
All right.
So when are you going to ask
me, I've had my own you for a while.
Hey, buddy, he's off my girl, man,
or do you want a knuckle sandwich?
Cool, it, guys.
Your girl says who says me, Pipsqueak.
All right, so a little bit of a discussion
over a girl, very common as well.
Yes.
We'll be looking at
some of these words that
were maybe a little bit difficult in
the dialogue in language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
Well, we've got five phrases
and words from the dialogue.
Now, the first thing we heard
was Sandy said, hey, yeah.
Hey, yeah.
All right.
No, an interjection away of
saying hi, but very old fashioned.
Hey, yeah.
Basically, hi, you or hey, you.
Yep.
Hey, so hey, I guess you would
still use it today though, right?
Yeah, it's still a normal
way to greet someone.
All right, very friendly.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
And what about our second word?
Well, Sandy S. Tracy, how are you?
And Tracy replies, I'm swell.
I'm swell.
Swell.
I'm just swell.
When you are swell, you are great.
You're great.
And again, swell is an old
fashioned way of saying
I'm good or I'm great,
but you would still hear it.
Yes.
And it also is used to describe things.
That was a swell party.
Okay, swell.
Yeah.
All right.
Now for our next word, they got
into a fight and Tracy said, cool it, guys.
Cool it.
So why don't we listen to some
examples of cool it before we explain it?
Example one.
Just cool it.
Now is not the right time to get angry.
Example two.
You need to cool it and stop yelling at me.
Example three.
Don't cry, Pam.
Just cool it.
You'll be okay.
All right.
So cool it, guys.
Basically, it means relax.
Take it easy.
Yeah.
All right.
Okay.
This is one my dad used to say
to me and my sister is all the time.
Cool it, kid.
Stop fighting.
Very good.
So it is still very commonly
used, I would say.
Yep.
All right.
Now for our last two words, these
are a little bit more old fashioned.
Yes.
Straight from 1952, they
talk about a knuckle sandwich.
All right.
He says, do you want a knuckle
sandwich, a knuckle sandwich?
What are we talking about here?
All right.
Well, on your hand.
You have above your fingers,
you have your knuckles.
Okay.
So those are the bumpy parts on my hand.
The bones on the top part of your hand.
So he's basically saying, do
you want me to punch you?
Right.
Do you want me to hit you
with my hand, with my fist?
So it's in very informal way of
saying a punch, a knuckle sandwich.
I'll give you a knuckle sandwich.
Right.
And for our last word,
he called Tony called
Sandy, a pip squeak,
pip squeak, pip squeak.
A pip squeak.
Now this is kind of an insult,
but again, very old fashioned.
Yes.
A pip squeak is a very small person, right?
A small person who is
not strong or not powerful.
So a small and weak person, pip squeak.
I guess nowadays you
can still call somebody
pip squeak, but maybe
in a lighter sense.
It would be a little bit funny
to call someone a pip squeak.
Okay.
So a pip squeak.
Why don't we listen to our dialogue again?
We're going to slow it
down a little bit so you
can get all these words
that we just looked at.
And then we'll come back
and look at some phrases.
Hey, Tracy.
How are you doing?
I'm swell, Sandy.
Hey, listen.
You want to go to the
sock hop with me this Friday?
It'll be a blast.
First of all, it's the Sadie Hawkins dance.
The girls got to ask the guys.
Also.
Oh, right.
So when are you going to ask me?
I've had my eye on you for a while.
Hey, buddy, he's off my girl, man.
Or do you want a knuckle sandwich?
Cool it, guys.
You are, girl.
Says who says me, pip squeak.
OK, so that was a little
bit easier to understand.
But some great 50s style phrases and words.
So why don't we look at some of
these phrases now in fluency builder?
Fluency builder.
All right, I'm fluency builder today.
We're going to look at three phrases.
Why don't we start with the first one?
Sandy said that the party will be a blast.
It'll be a blast.
To be a blast.
So if something is a blast, it's very fun.
It's entertaining.
Yes, really, really fun.
OK, so the party was a blast.
I had a great time last night.
It was a blast.
OK, very good.
So very fun times.
Yep.
And you'll still hear
this phrase used today.
Now the next one.
So Sandy said he had his eye on Tracy.
And he said, I've had my eye on you.
To have your eye on someone.
So if I have my eye on the
new iPhone that came out,
you are watching it
carefully because you want it.
OK, so I'm keeping my
attention on it because I want it.
I have my eye on that
sweater because it's on sale.
OK, so you really want that sweater.
Yep.
All right.
So to have your eye on
something or on someone, right?
And for our last phrase,
Tommy told Sandy, hey,
buddy, ease off my
girl, ease off, ease off.
Ease off.
All right, so why don't
we listen to some examples
of how we could use ease off
because it might be a little bit tricky.
And then we'll come back and talk about it.
Example one.
You need to ease off the junk food.
Example two.
Matt is putting so much
pressure on me these days.
I wish you would ease off.
Example three.
You're pushing Susie too much.
You need to ease off a bed.
OK, so it looks like you say this
phrase ease off when somebody
is putting pressure on you or doing
something to you that they shouldn't.
Right, maybe they're being too
intense or maybe annoying you.
So you tell him, hey, ease off.
Yeah, relax, stay back.
Stay away, very good.
So ease off, ease off my girlfriend.
Ease off the fatty foods.
All right, so take it easy, stay away from.
Yep.
OK, so some great phrases there.
I think it's a good idea for us to
listen to our dialogue one more time.
And then we'll come back and
talk a little bit more about the 1950s.
Hey, Tracy, how are you doing?
I'm swell, Sandy.
Hey, listen, you want to go to
the sock hop with me this Friday?
It'll be a blast.
First of all, it's the Sadie Hawkins dance.
The girls got to ask the guys also.
All right, so when are you going to ask me?
I've had my right on you for a while.
Hey, buddy, ease off my girl, man.
Or do you want a knuckle sandwich?
Cool, it guys.
Your girl says who?
Says me, Pipsqueak.
OK, so the 1950s, a nice era.
And this is the first
of a small series that
we're going to have
of different words and
phrases that were used back in
the 1950s, 1960s, 1970s, et cetera.
That's right.
So a little bit more time travel is
coming up here in English Pives.
Exactly, because a lot
of these phrases are
still used and you might
even see them in movies
or if you're talking
to somebody that was
maybe born in these eras, they
might even still use them today.
That's right.
So do you guys know any English
phrases or slangs from the 1950s?
Why don't you visit our website at
EnglishPod.com to tell us about it.
All right.
We'll see you guys there.
And also, if you have
questions or comments,
please leave them on the
comments section as well.
Thanks for listening.
And until next time.
Bye-bye.